很多人都问过阿波罗制导计算机（AGC）的“动词/名词”是什么意思
A lot of you guys have asked about the whole Verb/Noun the thing on the Apollo guidance computer.
那咱今天就来聊聊这个
Well, that's what we're talking about today - in brief - on Vintage Space.
不少人总爱说现代的手机算力比AGC高到不知道哪里去
The comparison is often made that
a modern cell phone has more computing power than the Apollo guidance computer.
这倒也没错 但iPhone没法送你去月球
Well, yes, that's true, but your iPhone can't get you to the Moon;
它没那软件
it doesn't exactly have that software...
而实际上 AGC真正的美在于
And really, the beauty of the Apollo guidance computer is
它高度的集成与特别定制的软件
in how tightly packed and specifically organized that software really was.
一说起计算机或者智能手机
When we think of a computer or even a smartphone
我们上来想到的是屏幕 文字编辑 键盘之类的操控界面
we think of interfaces that are familiar to us like a screen and a word processor and a keyboard...
甚至就是一个计算器的样子
and even just a basic calculator.
而AGC这些都没有
Well the Apollo guidance computer had none of those things.
它设计用来在登月过程中执行一组特定的程序
It was designed to run a very small set of specifically designed programs needed to run a mission to the Moon,
比如检查惯导平台的校正 启动发动机等
things like checking the guidance platform alignment and firing the engines.
阿波罗任务中几乎一切都是由计算机完成的
Everything on an Apollo mission was done through the computer
登月来回要按大约10500次按键
and it took about 10,500 keystrokes to get one mission to the Moon and back.
但因为AGC没有我们平常熟悉的操控界面
But because the guidance computer didn't have those interfaces that we're used to
比如全键盘和文字编辑器之类的东西
like keyboards and word processors and all those things,
所以输入方式上会有些许不同
the inputs had to be a little bit different.
这是AGC的界面
This is the interface of the Apollo guidance computer,
名字叫DSKY 是“display”和“keyboard”合起来的缩写
the display and keyboard commonly referred to as the DSKY (diss-key).
注意到它有屏幕 有按键
Now you can see that it does have a screen, it does have keys,
但和我们家用电脑的屏幕不太一样
but it's not a typical screen like we're used to using on our home computers.
它没有字幕按键 屏幕也不会以单词的形式显示信息
There aren't alphabetical keys and the screen doesn't list information in words.
实际上 它的键盘和我们使用过的完全不一样
In fact, this keyboard is anything but common to us.
那么宇航员是如何操控DSKY的呢？
So how exactly did the astronauts use the DSKY?
其实它为宇航员们提供了一种非常简单的交互方式
Well it actually offered a very simplistic interface for crews.
首先是上方的警示灯 COMP ACTY表示计算机正在运行程序
Starting with the warning lights. COMP ACTY lit up when the computer was running a program.
UPLINK ACTY表示有从地面接收到的数据
UPLINK ACTY was lit when there was data being received from the ground.
TEMP表示平台温度超出阈值
TEMP lit up when the temperature of the platform was out of tolerance.
NO ATT表示惯性子系统无法提供姿态参考
NO ATT lit up when the inertial subsystem could not provide an attitude reference.
GIMBAL LOCK表示中央万向节角度大于70度
GIMBAL LOCK lit up when the middle gimbal angle was greater than 70 degrees
表示飞船此时非常接近危险的万向节死锁的情况
signifying that the spacecraft was close to hitting that deadly gimbal lock scenario.
STBY表示计算机系统处于待命状态
STBY lit up when the computer system was on standby.
PROG表示计算机正在等待乘员输入额外的信息以完成程序运行
PROG lit up when the computer was waiting for additional information
to be entered by the crew to complete a program.
KEY REL表示计算机需要控制DSKY以完成程序
KEY REL lit up when the computer needed control of the DSKY to complete a program.
RESTART表示计算机处于重启程序中
RESTART was lit up when the computer was in the restart program.
OPR ERR计算机检测到键盘输入错误
表示OPR ERR was lit when the computer detected an error on the keyboard.
TRACKER表示一个交会雷达耦合数据单元失效
And TRACKER lit up with one of the obstacle coupling units failed.
登月舱DSKY有三个额外的警示灯：一个表示自动驾驶故障
The lunar module DSKY had three additional warnings: one to signify a problem with the autopilot
两个表示登月舱高度和速度有问题
and two more to signify problems with the altitude and velocity of the lunar module spacecraft.
除了这十个警示灯 还有下面其他的按钮
In addition to these 10 warning keys we have other keys:
动词 名词 加号 减号 数字键 和几个指令键
Verb, Noun, Plus, Minus, numbers, and handful of command keys.
所以显然没法敲一行类似“运行惯导平台校正程序”这样的命令进去
So there's no obvious way to write in a command like "run guidance platform alignment program,"
那么宇航员是如何用DSKY与AGC交互的呢？
so how exactly did the astronauts actually interface with the computer using the DSKY?
这就要说到“动词/名词”形式了
Well, this is where nouns and verbs come in,
想要理解这个 我们要先把宇宙飞船放在一边
but to understand this we actually kind of need to leave the spacecraft for a second
回到地面 比如咱们来到了纽约市大街上
and go down to maybe the streets of New York City.
想象你在纽约旅游 你又不会说鸟语
So imagine you're in New York City, you are a tourist, and you don't really speak any English;
自己脑子里只会大概五个词 而它们也不可能组成一句
you've got about five words in your arsenal, none of them include
“您好 这个城市有啥好吃的餐馆吗？”这样的话
"excuse me, but which way to a lovely restaurant in this fine neighborhood of the city?"
于是你找到一个警察 你觉得这人能带你到你想去的地方
So you find a policeman knowing that this is the kind of person
who might be able to direct you towards what it is you're looking for.
你到警察面前 使用其中一个词告诉他你想要做什么
So you go up to the policeman and you use one of your words to tell him what it is you want to do.
那个词是“吃” 而“吃”是动词
That word is "eat," and that is a verb.
可纽约好吃的多了去了
But there's a lot of food in New York City to choose from
所以你得指定你要吃什么
so you have to define what it is you want to eat,
于是你又说出了一个词“披萨” 这是个名词
and so you use one of your other words, "pizza," which is a noun.
你听明白了吗？
So do you see where we're going with this?
就像你用小学二年级英语和警察叔叔对话的场景一样
Just like your awkward, broken English conversation with the New York City policeman,
AGC处理的所有数据都是用“动词/名词”形式传递的
all data going through the Apollo guidance computer used verbs and nouns.
用动词确定要执行的动作
The verb is defined as the action being taken
用名词确定该动作执行在哪组数据上
and the noun is defined as the data set being acted on.
我们在现实中的计算机也有类似的操作
There's actually a really simple computer-based version of this that we all use
只是我们很多没有注意到 因为没人管它叫“动词/名词”
but don't really think about because it's not expressed as a noun and a verb
这个例子就是打印文件
printing a document.
你选择了“打印” 这就是动词
If you select print, that is the verb.
而对应的文件名就是名词 就是计算机要处理的数据（本例中数据就是文件）
The file name is the noun, which is basically the data set
(or in this case document) that that verb is acting on.
所以宇航员就是这样用“动词/名词”将数据输入到AGC的
So the astronauts inputted all their data using nouns and verbs into the Apollo guidance computer.
动词名词各100种 各自定义了AGC在任务中会执行的程序
There were 100 sets of noun verb pairs all defining a specific thing
that the Apollo guidance computer would do on a mission.
我们来举个例子看看 如果你输入了 动词-37
So let's look at an example. Let's say you enter verb 37 --
意思是告诉计算机你要更换程序
that tells the computer that you are about to make a change to the program.
然后你输入31 告诉计算机运行名词-31 即交会程序
Then you hit 3-1, and that tells the computer to run noun 31, which is a targeted rendezvous program.
其他组合还有很多
And there are a host of others!
动词-50 名词-18 对应角度机动
The crew could request maneuver angles with verb 50 noun 18,
动词-06 名词-18 对应在机动过程中监看变化
the crew could monitor changes while a maneuver was in progress with verb 06 noun 18,
动词-06 名词-84 对应下次机动改变速度
or even request velocity change required for the next maneuver using verb 06 noun 84.
当一组动词名词被输入进计算机 DSKY上也会显示对应的信息
Once the noun and verb pairing was entered into the computer, the relevant information was displayed on the DSKY.
当然 如你所想 像登月这么庞大的工程
And of course as you can expect when doing something big like going to the moon
程序也会有很多种 名词动词也会有很多种
there were different kinds of programs, so different kinds of nouns and verbs.
常用动词 00-37用于显示 监看 更新数据 需要后接名词
Regular verbs verbs 00 - 37 were used to display, monitor, or update data meaning they needed a noun;
因为它们要处理数据
they needed something to be acting on.
而动词49-99则不需要后接名词即可执行程序
Whereas extended verbs were verbs 49 - 99 and they didn't need a noun to execute a program;
这些动词会命令计算机执行一个简单的操作
they told the computer to perform a simple operation.
剩下就是恰饭了 不翻了 视频详情里可以找到AGC的使用说明书
Of course, there is so much more to the Apollo guidance computer than this super quick look at nouns and
verbs, and so I would urge you all to
check out Frank O'Brien's book "The
Apollo Guidance Computer," which, as I've
said before and I always remind Frank is
said with love and in jest, it is more
than you ever need to know about how the
Apollo guidance computer worked! So do
you guys have other questions about the
Apollo guidance computer? I'm not saying
I can answer them off the top of my head
but I can read and then figure it out
for you! Let me know if any of this makes
sense or if none of this makes sense or
if you have other things you would just
love to figure out about how the Apollo
guidance computer worked! Leave all of
those and of course any other comments
and things you would like to see covered
in future episodes down in the comment
section. Be sure to follow me on Twitter
and on Instagram for new Vintage Space-ish
content every day of the week, and
things are going to be changing just a
little bit on this channel but I'm still
doing it classic Vintage Space education
episodes every Monday or Tuesday
(depending on upload schedule) so if you
don't want to miss any of those be sure
to subscribe just so you never miss a
video!    :)